Chapter 82. The honor and glory of whailing.
There are some enterprises in which a careful disorderliness is the true method.
The more I dive into this matter of whailing and push my researches up to
the very spring head of it, so much the more am I impressed with its great
honorableness and antiquity, and especially when I find so many great
demigods and heroes, prophets of all sort, who one way or another have shed
distinction upon it, I am transported with the reflection that I myself
belong, though subordinately, to so emlazed, a fraternity,
the gallant Perseus, son of Jupiter, was the first whaleman, and to the eternal
honor of our calling be it said that the first whale attacked by our brotherhood
was not killed with any sorted intent.
Those were the nightly days of our profession, when we only bore arms to
sucker the distressed, not to fill men's lamp feeders. Everyone knows the fine
story of Perseus and Andromeda. How the lovely Andromeda, the daughter of a
king, was tied to a rock on the sea coast. And as Leviathan was in the very
act of carrying her off, Perseus, the prince of whaleman, intrepidly
advancing, harpooned the monster, and delivered and married the maid. It was
an admirable artistic exploit rarely achieved by the best harpooners of the
present day in as much as this Leviathan was slain at the very first dart. And
let no man doubt this arite story. For in the ancient Japa, now Jaffa, on the
Syrian coast, in one of the pagan temples, there stood for many ages the
vast skeleton of a whale, which the city's legends and all the inhabitants
asserted to be the identical bones of the monster that Persus slew. When the
Romans took Japa, the same skeleton was carried to Italy in triumph. What seems
most singular and suggestively important in this story is this. It was from Japa
that Jonah set sail.
Akin to the adventure of Perseus and Andromeda, indeed by some supposed to be
indirectly derived from it, is that famous story of St. George and the
dragon. Which dragon I maintain to have been a whale. For in many old chronicles
whales and dragons are strangely jumbled together, and often stand for each
other. Thou art as a lion of the waters, and as a dragon of the sea, saith
Ezekiel, hereby plainly meaning a whale.
In truth, some versions of the Bible use that word itself. Besides, it would much
subtract from the glory of the exploit had St. George but encountered a
crawling reptile of the land instead of doing battle with the great monster of
the deep. Any man may kill a snake, but only a perseus, a St. George, a coffin
have the heart in them to march boldly up to a whale.
Let not the modern paintings of this scene mislead us. For though the
creature encountered by that valiant whaleman of old is vaguely represented
of a griffin-like shape, and though the battle is depicted on land, and the
saint on horseback, yet considering the great ignorance of those times, when the
true form of the whale was unknown to artists, and considering that, as in
Perseus's case, St. George's whale might have crawled up out of the sea on the
beach, and considering that the animal ridden by St. George might have been
only a large seal or seahorse. Bearing all this in mind, it will not appear
altogether incompatible with the sacred legend in the ancientest drafts of the
scene to hold this so-called dragon no other than the great Leviathan himself.
In fact, placed before the strict and piercing truth, this whole story will
fare like that fish, flesh, and foul idol of the Philistines, Dagon by name,
who being planted before the ark of Israel, his horse's head, and both the
palms of his hands fell off from him, and only the stump or fishy part of him
remained. Thus then, one of our own noble stamp, even a whaleman, is the
tutelary guardian of England, and by good rights we harpineers of Nantucket,
should be enrolled in the most noble order of St. George. And therefore, let
not the knights of that honorable company, none of whom, I venture to say,
have ever had to do with a whale like their great patron, let them never eye
an a nantucketer with disdain, since even in our woolen frocks and tred
trousers, we are much better entitled to St. George's decoration than they.
Whether to admit Hercules among us or not, concerning this, I long remained
dubious. For though, according to the Greek mythologies, that antique crockett
and kit Carson, that brrawy doer of rejoicing good deeds, was swallowed down
and thrown up by a whale. Still, whether that strictly makes a whaleman of him,
that might be mooded. It nowhere appears that he ever actually harpooned his
fish, unless indeed from the inside.
Nevertheless, he may be deemed a sort of involuntary whaleman. At any rate, the
whale caught him if he did not the whale. I claim him for one of our clan.
But by the best contradictory authorities, this Grecian story of
Hercules and the whale is considered to be derived from the still more ancient
Hebrew story of Jonah and the whale and vice versa. Certainly, they are very
similar. If I claim the demigod, then why not the prophet?
Nor do heroes, saints, demiggods, and prophets alone comprise the whole role
of our order. Our grandmaster is still to be named. For like royal kings of old
times, we find the headwaters of our fraternity in nothing short of the great
gods themselves. That wondrous oriental story is now to be rehearsed from the
sher which gives us the dread Vishnu, one of the three persons of the godhead
of the Hindus, gives us this divine Vishnu himself for our Lord. Vishnu who
by the first of his 10 earthly incarnations has forever set apart and
sanctified the whale. When Brahma or the god of gods saith the shastra resolved
to recreate the world after one of its periodical dissolutions, he gave birth
to Vishnu to preside over the work. But the vadas or mystical books whose
perusal would seem to have been indispensable to Vishnu before beginning
the creation and which therefore must have contained something in the shape of
practical hints to young architects.
These vdas were lying at the bottom of the waters. So Vishnu became incarnate
as a whale and sounding down in him to the uttermost depths rescued the sacred
volumes. Was not this Vishnu a whaleman then? Even as a man who rides a horse is
called a horseman.
Perseus, St. George, Hercules, Jonah, and Vishnu. There's a member role for
you. What club but the whaleman's can head off like that?